Finding Aid for the Albert Boime Papers LSC.1834
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Research materials, 1941-2008
  - Late 20th Century Art, 1988-2003
    - Outsider art, 1992 (Box 106, Folder 6)
      Copies of student paper "Are There Any True Outsiders? Or Are All Artists Crazy?: An Examination of a Los Angeles Exhibit of Outsider Art" by Heather Propes.
    - Muralismo, 1997-1998 (Box 106, Folder 7)
      Papers regarding muralism, correspondence with Shifra Goldman and others, and photocopies of images. Some materials in Spanish.
    - Contemporary American social artists, undated (Box 106, Folder 8)
      Project description for "Hidden Visions: Contemporary American Social Artists" (researcher unclear) and notes.
  - Miscellaneous 20th Century Topics, Bulk 1997-2003, 1969-2006
    Boime's research on a range of topics in the 20th century that are not clearly attributable to a specific project. Filed by topic.
    - McLuhan, 1969 (Box 106, Folder 9)
      Clippings from The New York Times Magazine.
    - Robert Rosenbloom, 2006 (Box 106, Folder 10)
      Newspaper article about curator Robert Rosenbloom's death.
    - Ad Reinhardt, 2000 (Box 106, Folder 11)
      Notes, correspondence regarding Freedom of Information Act files, and library request forms for Smithsonian research activities.
    - France 1968, ca. 1989 (Box 106, Folder 12)
      Student paper "Getting Back to Zero: The Climate in Paris, 1968 and the Work of Jean-Luc Godard and Daniel Buren" by Nora Halpern Brougher. Folder also contains some clippings.
    - Millennial - 21st century, ca. 1984, 1997-2000 (Box 106, Folder 13)
      Clippings and notes.
    - New landscape theory - Olwig, undated (Box 106, Folder 14)
      Article by Kenneth Olwig "Recovering the Substantive Nature of Landscape" and notes.
    - Evolution - bio, undated (Box 106, Folder 15)
      Clippings, photocopies, and brochure for symposium "Evolution! Facts and Fallacies" by the UCLA Center for the Study of Evolution and the Origin of Life.
    - Haake, 1987 (Box 106, Folder 16)
    - Bauhaus, 1997, 2001 (Box 106, Folder 17)
      Syllabi for course on Bauhaus by Loewenberg, paper "Towards an Understanding of the Bauhaus View of Technology and Science: A Spiritual Connection" by Naomi A. Weiss, brochure for architecture exhibition at MOCA, photocopies, and e-mail correspondence.
    - Turks, undated (Box 106, Folder 18)
      Traveler's map for Istanbul, Turkey.
    - Mexican Revolution, 1997-1998, 2002 (Box 107, Folder 1)
      Syllabi for course on Mexican Revolution since 1910, Diego Rivera exhibition brochure, LACMA Exhibition publication for "Mexican Masterpieces from the Bernard and Edith Lewin Collection," and student paper "Diego Rivera and the Rockefeller Center Scandal" by Thomas Tokuza.
    - Collectors, undated (Box 107, Folder 2)
      Student papers on various galleries and museums.
    - Post-1945 abstraction, 1998-1999 (Box 107, Folder 3)
      Notes, clippings, and exhibition brochure about Jackson Pollock.
    - New NY school, 2000 (Box 107, Folder 4)
    - Pop, undated (Box 107, Folder 5)
    - Pop, 1996 (Box 107, Folder 6)
      Copy of paper "Pop Art as Consumerist Realism" by David Kunzle.
    - Conceptual, undated (Box 107, Folder 7)
      Catalog of works by Robert Morris.
    - Haring, 1997 (Box 107, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, images of work by Keith Haring, and promotional material from Kantor Gallery.
    - Freud and culture, 2000 (Box 107, Folder 9)
      Card and pamphlet on "Freud: Conflict and Culture" (exhibition at the Skirball Cultural Center).
    - Castellane Gallery, 1977 (Box 107, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, print, and notes.
    - 2010, 2005-2006 (Box 107, Folder 11)
      Correspondence, Art History 54 class evaluation summary, and National Park Service bound booklet "Statue of Liberty National Monument: New Directions."
    - Epilogue, 2001 (Box 107, Folder 12)
    - Recentering, 2003 (Box 107, Folder 13)
      E-mail correspondence with Raymond Barglow.
    - The ugly, undated (Box 107, Folder 14)
      Photocopy of article "The Ugly" by Mark Cousins.
    - Neiman, ca. 2001 (Box 107, Folder 15)
      Notes on LeRoy Neiman, photocopied article about Neiman, and exhibition brochures of his work.
    - Flyers, ca. 1997-1998 (Box 107, Folder 16)
      Flyers for upcoming events surrounding Judaism and Che Guevara.
  - Early Career, 1962-1970
    Materials collected during Boime's early career. Most topics relate to France or French research. Arranged topically.
    - Ladies, undated (Box 107, Folder 17)
      Miscellaneous pages from draft about Statue of Liberty, notes, and paper by Heidi Hebert on "Cindy Sherman's Masquerade: A Recontextualization of the Female Image."
    - Renaissance, undated (Box 107, Folder 18)
    - Salon de Refuses, 1962, 1968 (Box 107, Folder 19)
      Notes, draft of paper "The Salon des Refuses" with edits, and photocopies.
    - French art/National Archives (1 of 2), ca. 1962 (Box 107, Folder 20)
      Notes including some from French National Archives and draft "Piero and Seurat: A Neglected Stylistic Link" with edits. Folder also includes photocopies and correspondence. Some materials in French.
    - French art/National Archives (1 of 2), ca. 1962 (Box 108, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous French art research, 1965 (Box 108, Folder 2)
      Notes and correspondence, likely related to research in French Archives. Some materials in French.
    - Miscellaneous 19th century, undated (Box 108, Folder 3)
    - Lusker, 1970 (Box 108, Folder 4)
      Clippings, notes, and photocopies.
    - Berea notes, 1970 (Box 108, Folder 5)
      Photocopies and "Berea notes."
    - Endnotes, undated (Box 108, Folder 6)
      Endnotes to unidentified publication, photocopies, passport photo, and comics.
    - Articles, undated (Box 108, Folder 7)
      Notes and drafts of articles about Seurat, Piero della Francesca, and Charles Bouleau.
    - French correspondence, 1962, 1964-1966 (Box 108, Folder 8)
    - Business correspondence - U.S. and abroad, 1966-1967 (Box 108, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Research Topics, 1954-2006
    Materials relating to specific research topics that are not clearly related to any of Boime's larger projects. The subseries includes research on a French petition, pompiers (firefighters), music, architecture, children, and unconventional scholars. The subseries is arranged by subject.
    - Petition, undated (Box 108, Folder 10)
      Drafts of "An Unpublished Petition Exemplifying the Oneness of the Community of Nineteenth-Century French Artists." Other materials include notes and photocopies.
    - Petition, undated (Box 108, Folder 11)
    - Pompiers (Firefighters), undated (Box 108, Folder 12)
    - Pompiers (Firefighters), undated (Box 108, Folder 13)
      Miscellaneous pages of article on pompiers and notes.
    - Music, undated (Box 108, Folder 14)
      Paper on censorship in rap (authorship unclear).
    - Music, 1988, 1998, 2002 (Box 108, Folder 15)
      Photocopied articles, conference on music in 1492: outline and program, newspaper clipping, and promotional comic "Bebop to Hip hop" produced by City of LA Cultural Affairs Department.
    - Music - 19th-20th century, 1981 (Box 108, Folder 16)
      Notes and paper "Johannes Kreisler and Ludwig van Beethoven: The Image of the Romantic Composer for the Nineteenth Century" by Janet Marquardt.
    - USA music 20th century, 2002 (Box 108, Folder 17)
      Dissertation prospectus by Charles Hiroshi Garrett "Struggling to Define a Nation: Reconstructing American Music in the 20th Century" with edits. Folder also includes a brochure for Smithsonian exhibition on Woody Guthrie.
    - Songs of revolution, 2000, 2006 (Box 108, Folder 18)
      Correspondence and lyrics to anti-establishment songs.
    - Architecture, undated (Box 109, Folder 1)
    - Architecture, undated (Box 109, Folder 2)
      Notes and draft of "The Campus Architecture: A Bright Future After a Sad Beginning" with edits.
    - Neo-Boydell, 1997 (Box 109, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and catalog of Boydell collection.
    - Gear - baby portraits, undated (Box 109, Folder 4)
      Josephine Gear curriculum vitae, fellowship application, and paper on baby portraits.
    - Children, ca. 1976-1977 (Box 109, Folder 5)
      Notes on childbirth, copy of paper and bibliography of Mexican Muralists, and copy of paper "Babes in the Woods" by Mary Warlick.
    - Children's books, 1998 (Box 109, Folder 6)
      Clippings from UCLA Librarian magazine.
    - Anderson, 2000 (Box 109, Folder 7)
      Outline and draft of "The Creation of the Rome Prize for Engraving" (possibly by Susanne Anderson).
    - Medieval, undated (Box 109, Folder 8)
    - Bergstrom - library, 1997 (Box 109, Folder 9)
      Library reports from Janet Bergstrom written for "Guide to Resources in French Studies" and article "Jean Renoir's Return to France" by Janet Bergstrom.
    - Chemung County Historical Society, 1993 (Box 109, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and exhibition proposal by Chemung County Historical Society titled "Through Mark Twain's Eyes."
    - Offbeat scholars, 1996 (Box 109, Folder 11)
      Correspondence with John Alan Walker, including copies of his publications.
    - Shticks, 1998 (Box 109, Folder 12)
      Collection of clever interpretations of conventional written works including "Have Yourself a Microsoft Christmas", correspondence, and paper by John Alan Walker "Out-Side Historicisms and Other Boo-Boos in the Manet Secular Modernist Literature."
    - Senior, Nassau, undated (Box 109, Folder 13)
      Notes from "Conversations" by William Senior Nassau.
    - Marksman manual, ca. 1954 (Box 109, Folder 14)
      Shooting manual entitled "Hits Count" published by The Infantry School in Fort Benning, Georgia.
  - Eastern Europe, 1992-2005
    - Totalitarianism, undated (Box 109, Folder 15)
      Paper "Totalitarisme" by Krzysztof Pomian, draft of "On the notion of the 'exceptionality' of the 'Final Solution'" by Saul Friedlander, and draft of "Remembrance and Revisionism: Denial of the Armenian and Jewish Genocides" by Michael Blacher. Some materials in French.
    - Russia, 2000 (Box 109, Folder 16)
      Correspondence with Irina Tatarinova, paper "Ilya Repin and his Procession of the Cross in the Kursk Province" of unclear authorship, and paper by Tatarinova for Boime to proofread.
    - Russian A-G, 1999-2005 (Box 110, Folder 1)
      Clippings, Szymon Bojko curriculum vitae, course information, papers, and exhibition brochures. Folder also includes paper by Kathryn Goodyear "The Influence of the Icon and the Iconic Style on the Russian Artists of the Early Twentieth Century," e-mail correspondence, and writing samples from Masha Galkina.
    - Three days in Moscow: the August putsch, 1992-1993 (Box 110, Folder 2)
      Photographs, conference materials, correspondence and notes for conference "Three Days in Moscow: The August Putsch" by International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House.
    - East European, 1995 (Box 110, Folder 3)
      correspondence, photocopies of Polish statuary/monuments, papers, and newsletters.
    - Cold War, 2002, 2004 (Box 110, Folder 4)
      E-mail correspondence with Clare Spark, articles, and brochure for Exhibition "Arnold Mesches: FBI Files" at the Skirball Cultural Center.
    - Railroad, undated (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - Perestroika, 1992-1993
    - Perestroika, undated (Box 110, Folder 6)
      Draft of "Hollow Icons and Perestroika in the Glasnost Period" with edits.
    - Perestroika, 1993 (Box 110, Folder 7)
      Draft of "Perestroika and the Destabilization of the Soviet Monuments" with edits (2 copies) and faxed copies of articles/clippings.
    - East Europe and modernity, undated (Box 110, Folder 8)
      Draft of paper "New Visions of Modernity" by Rostislav Svacha and draft pages from paper "Perestroika and the Destabilization of Soviet Monuments."
    - Romania (1 of 2), ca. 1992 (Box 110, Folder 9)
      Drafts of "Perestroika and the Destabilization of the Soviet Monuments", drafts of "Hollow Icons and Perestroika in the Glasnost Period" with edits, photocopies, correspondence, clippings, notes, and catalog of Czechoslovakian art.
    - Romania (2 of 2), ca. 1992 (Box 144, Folder 3)
      Drafts of "Perestroika and the Destabilization of the Soviet Monuments," drafts of "Hollow Icons and Perestroika in the Glasnost Period" with edits, photocopies, correspondence, clippings, notes, and catalog of Czechoslovakian art.
  - Photography, 1975-2004
    - Photography, 1987-1991, 2000-2004 (Box 111, Folder 1)
      Notes, "History of Photography" quarterly magazine about Ingres, photo newsletter, correspondence, notes, Art History 253 syllabus for Spring 1991 (Modernism, Photography and the Body), photocopies, articles, brochures, and exhibition catalogs.
    - Photo symposium, 1975-1979, 1984-1986 (Box 111, Folder 2)
      Clippings, photocopies, brochures, and pamphlets.
    - Photo, 1998-2003 (Box 111, Folder 3)
      Photocopies, brochures, clippings, pages from untitled draft, booklets (artists include Ansel Adams, Edgar Degas, and Walker Evans), and draft of introduction to untitled paper.
  - Science and Art, 1983-2004
    Materials correspond to Boime's research on relationships between science and art, including an interest in technology. Filed by topic.
    - Atmospheric optics in art, undated (Box 111, Folder 4)
      Copy of "Atmospheric Optics in Art" by Stanley David Gedzelman.
    - Science and modernism, undated (Box 111, Folder 5)
      Dissertation Proposal from William Barr.
    - Science and art, 1986 (Box 111, Folder 6)
      Photocopied articles, information on sci-realism, notes, and correspondence.
    - Science, bulk 2000-2004, 1994 (Box 111, Folder 7)
      Articles, notes, correspondence, and clippings.
    - Responsibility of science, 1990 (Box 111, Folder 8)
      Articles, notes, and clippings.
    - Science and moon, ca. 1983 (Box 112, Folder 1)
      Notes, course syllabus, and student paper. Some materials in German.
    - Chaos, ca. 1990 (Box 112, Folder 2)
      Press release and copy of paper/lecture regarding chaos theory.
    - Physics, undated (Box 112, Folder 3)
      Slide lists for "Physics and Painting" and "Color and Light in Painting."
    - Information super highway, 2000 (Box 112, Folder 4)
    - Fax/Computer use, 1991-1992, 1994 (Box 112, Folder 5)
      UCLA memos and information regarding computer access and UCLA library online. Folder also includes invoices.
  - Art Theory, 1960-2002
    Various papers, correspondence, and articles relating to theoretical approaches to art interpretation, including a brief paper by Boime outlining his preference for social history perspectives. The subseries is arranged by topic.
    - Methodological, 1988-1989 (Box 112, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and copy of Wayne Andersen paper "Rebuilding Art History."
    - Theory, etc., 1999-2002 (Box 112, Folder 7)
      Notes, photocopied articles, conference program and description on "Aesthetics and Semiotics: New Visions and New Voices," various papers by students and colleagues including collection of works by Howard Singerman, and e- mail correspondence.
    - More theory, 2000 (Box 112, Folder 8)
      E-mail correspondence, notes, article by Erwin Panofsky, and brief writing "Why I Prefer Social Art History" (likely composed by Boime).
    - Words of wisdom, undated (Box 112, Folder 9)
      Words of wisdom from Hopi Nation and unidentified source.
    - Status of Art History, 2002 (Box 112, Folder 10)
      Notes and e-mail correspondence with David Kunzle.
    - What is writing?, 1960 (Box 112, Folder 11)
      Copy of "Bird's Eye View," a short story submitted by Boime to the Samuel Goldwyn Writing Contest.
    - Literature of art, 1976 (Box 112, Folder 12)
    - Whither Art History?, 1987, 1989 (Box 144, Folder 4)
      Photocopies, articles, notes, clippings, and correspondence.
    - Social history of art, 1986 (Box 144, Folder 5)
      Copy of lecture by Leonard Folgarait "The Social History of Art," correspondence, grad student symposium agenda and abstracts, photocopies, and papers by Stephen Couch. Some materials in French.
  - Miscellaneous International Topics, 1994-2004
    Boime's research on countries and topics such as Mexico, Asian art, Japonisme, and Africa. Arranged by topic.
    - Tijuana, undated (Box 112, Folder 13)
    - Mexico, 2003-2004 (Box 112, Folder 14)
      Notes, correspondence, and photocopies.
    - Mexico, undated (Box 112, Folder 15)
      Notes, copies of images, and draft of "Masonic Influence on Nineteenth-Century Mexican History Painting" with edits.
    - Asian bias, 1995 (Box 112, Folder 16)
      Catalog of works by Xu Bing, clippings, and copy of "No Questions, No Answers: 'China' and a Book from the Sky" by Stanley K. Abe.
    - Asian American art, ca. 1997, 2000 (Box 113, Folder 1)
      Slide list, notes, and brochure for Arts of Pacific Asia show.
    - Japanism II, ca. 1992 (Box 113, Folder 2)
      Notes, student paper on "Japanism in Japan" by Wil (Yih-Liang) Lin, papers on imperialism, and photocopies.
    - Pilipino, 1994 (Box 113, Folder 3)
      Notes, postcard, and announcements for UCLA Pilipino Cultural Events.
    - India, undated (Box 113, Folder 4)
      Notes, possibly for a lecture.
    - Africa, 1995-1996 (Box 113, Folder 5)
      Clippings, gallery catalog of works by Joseph Bertiers at the Santa Monica Museum of Art, and notes.
    - Race and ethnicity notes, undated (Box 113, Folder 6)
    - Worlds fairs, undated (Box 113, Folder 7)
    - Kienholz, 1996, 1998 (Box 113, Folder 8)
    - "Body Around" exhibition, Kienholz, 1998, 2004 (Box 113, Folder 9)
      Correspondence related to student Cheol-Woong Sim, draft of "Taking Seoul to Heart" by Albert and Myra Boime, and "Body Around" exhibition press release.
    - Japonisme, 1991, 1994 (Box 144, Folder 6)
      Annotated photocopies, guide to uses of tradition in Japanese art published by the Met, notes, bibliographies, correspondence, exhibition brochures, and articles. Some materials in French.
  - John James Audubon, 1994-1998
    Boime's research for publication "John James Audubon's Fanciful Flights." Materials arranged by type.
    - Audubon, ca. 1994 (Box 113, Folder 10)
      Notes, photocopies, and invoice.
    - Audubon, undated (Box 113, Folder 11)
      Business cards, clipping, and draft of "John James Audubon's Fanciful Flights" with edits. Folder originally titled Audie.
    - Audubon, undated (Box 113, Folder 12)
      Draft of "John James Audubon's Fanciful Flights" with edits.
    - Audubon, 1998 (Box 113, Folder 13)
      Correspondence, abstract, and several drafts of "John James Audubon's Fanciful Flights." Folder originally titled Audie-Bon.
  - Belshazzar, 1999-2006
    Boime's research for paper "Forecasting Belshazzar's Fall." Arranged by topic.
    - Belshazzar, undated (Box 113, Folder 14)
      Draft of "Forecasting Belshazzar's Fall."
    - Belshazzar, bulk 1999, 2005 (Box 113, Folder 15)
      Notes, correspondence, and draft of "Forecasting Belshazzar's Fall" with edits. Folder originally titled Shazam.
    - Belshazzar photos, 1999, 2004-2006 (Box 113, Folder 16)
      Correspondence, invoices and photo permissions, and copies of artwork (likely a piece entitled Belshazzar's Feast, by John Martin). Folder originally titled shazam photos.
    - Belshazzar's fall, undated (Box 113, Folder 17)
      Outline for lecture or paper "Belshazzar's Feast: Anglo-American Visions of the Apocalypse."
  - Olympics, 1984, 1986
    The subseries is arranged by date.
    - Los Angeles Olympics, 1984 (Box 114, Folder 1)
      Notes regarding the 1984 Los Angeles Olympic Games, annotated photocopies and correspondence regarding Olympic games, and copy of "Official 1984 Olympic Fine Art posters Catalog." Folder also includes "Olympic Arts Festival Catalog," copy of paper by Robert Kaplan "From Pre-Industrial to Industrial Worker," notes regarding Art History 125, press releases, and slides.
    - Olympics bibliographies, 1984 (Box 114, Folder 2)
      Photocopied articles, Italian 105 syllabus, and bibliographies on Olympics.
    - Olympics 1996 (Box 114, Folder 3)
      Clipping from the Christian Science Monitor regarding the 1996 Olympic Games and art.
  - Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, bulk 1984-1990, 1972
    Arranged by topic. Research on this subject can also be found in box 42.
    - Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, ca. 1972, 1984-1988 (Box 114, Folder 4)
      Notes, student papers and dissertation prospectus, correspondence, annotated photocopies, and bibliographies.
    - Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, undated (Box 114, Folder 5)
    - Victorian art, 1987, 1990 (Box 114, Folder 6)
  - Barbizon School, 2000
    This subseries is filed by date.
    - Barbizon, 2000 (Box 114, Folder 7)
      Photocopies, notes, correspondence, and catalog of Barbizon works. Some materials in French.
    - Barbizon guys, undated (Box 114, Folder 8)
      Copies of photos. Folder originally titled Barbie Guys.
    - Barbizon School - vol. 3, undated (Box 114, Folder 9)
      Notes and annotated photocopies about Barbizon school and Courbet. Folder originally titled Barbie Inc. - vol. 3. Some materials in French.
- Series 4: Lectures and conferences, 1972-2005
  Materials in this series were gathered by Boime through his participation in a variety of conferences, symposia, and lecture series. This series also contains drafts of lectures given by Boime. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  Series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Anecdote, 2005 (Box 115, Folder 1)
    Correspondence regarding plans to coordinate a conference on the anecdote. Folder also includes an informational sheet with definitions and interpretations of the anecdote.
  - Astroflash: Psychological portrait, 1992 (Box 115, Folder 2)
    Publication regarding Astrology. Materials in French.
  - Authentication symposia (1 of 5), 1995-1999, 2002 (Box 115, Folder 3)
    Correspondence and descriptive materials regarding Art Authentication Symposia, conference brochures, articles related to art appraisal, and informational materials regarding Smithsonian Professional Institutes and Retreats. Folder also includes correspondence with Andrew Brainerd, McCrone Research Institute, and American Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works.
  - Authentication symposia (2 of 5), 1995-1999, 2002 (Box 115, Folder 4)
  - Authentication symposia (3 of 5), 1995-1999, 2002 (Box 115, Folder 5)
  - Authentication symposia (4 of 5), 1995-1999, 2002 (Box 115, Folder 6)
  - Authentication symposia (5 of 5), 1995-1999, 2002 (Box 115, Folder 7)
  - Bielefeld symposium, 1985-1986 (Box 115, Folder 8)
    Draft of "Thomas Couture and the Privileging of Decadence," correspondence, notes and maps relating to Colloquium on 'Late Antiquity' sponsored by the Universitat Bielefeld (from Dr. Andre Stoll and Dr. Reinhart Herzog), and note cards on Romans of the Decadence for Boime's presentation at the symposium.
  - Civil rights symposium, ca. 1995 (Box 115, Folder 9)
    Symposium program and outline, notes, and photocopies.
  - Conferences, 1989, 1993 (Box 115, Folder 10)
    Conference and symposium information, application for conference travel funds, and correspondence.
  - Conference materials, 1985 (Box 115, Folder 11)
    Materials for UCLA Conference on Undergraduate Education. Folder also includes correspondence and an annotated photocopy "Involvement in Learning: Realizing the Potential of American Higher Education."
  - Duke lectures, 1996 (Box 115, Folder 12)
    Flyers for various lectures and correspondence regarding Duke's Edward H. Benenson Lecture Series.
  - Friedrich talk, undated (Box 115, Folder 13)
    Copy of "Caspar David Friedrich: The Monk on the Seashore."
  - Grand Central symposium, bulk 1983, 1988 (Box 115, Folder 14)